Guide to the Roman Galinski papers 1938-1974 CPAA 86-01
Central Connecticut State University, Publisher
Roman Galinski papers1938-1974
CPAA 86-01
3 boxes (3 linear ft.)
Central Connecticut State University
Galinski, Roman.
The collection consists of correspondence between Roman Galinski, who lived in the US since 1922, and other prominent political figures in Poland, who were sympathizers of Narodowa Demokracja, the Polish political party of nationalistic character. Mr. Galinski was himself very active in various political organizations and wrote extensively on the issue of Polish politics and nationalism, sometimes under a pseudonym Miroslaw Kosinski. He was a great opponent of Jozef Pilsudski and his political party, and on the other hand vas devoted to Roman Dmowski and his political views of Narodowa Demokracja. Collection includes photographs of local Polish American prominent figures. The collection contains a dozen or so anti-semitic publications from pre-war Poland.
Provenance
Material from the collection was donated to the archives by Roman Galinski family in 1986.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Roman Galinski was born on January 18, 1905 in Zbrucz, near Woloczysk, in Eastern Podole region, Poland. Galinski died on April 12, 1974 in Berlin, Connecticut. He immigrated to the US in 1922. He attended Alliance College and Union College. Galinski was editor of "Przewodnik Katolicki" from 1940 till 1945, a Polish language newspaper in New Britain, Connecticut, and also an author (sometimes under pseud. Miroslaw Kosinski). He wrote extensively to “Opoka” periodical run by Jedrzej Giertych, and to other nationalistic periodicals. He was a harsh critic of Pilsudski and Sanacja and devoted supporter of Roman Dmowski and activist in Narodowa Demokracja (nationalistic political group).
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence spanning 1938-1973, mostly with people from "Endecja", (Narodowa Demokracja) circles in America and Western Europe (N. Siemaszko, T. Bielecki, J. Giertych, A. Syski, Jan K. Tarnowski and others); Roman Dmowski letter to R. Galinski (which he later published under the title "Testament Romana Dmowskiego dla Polaka Amerykanina"), copies and manuscripts of his articles from Przewodnik Katolicki and other periodicals, anti-Pilsudski articles and pamphlets by other authors, 16 pamphlets and books about "Jewish question." Some pamphlets were photocopied without source information.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 2 groups:
General
Anti-semitic pamphlets
Access Points
Subject Names:
Dmowski Roman, 1864-1939.; Pilsudski Jozef 1867-1935.
Subject Organizations:
Narodowa Demokracja (Political party: Poland)
Subject Topics:
Polish Americans – Connecticut.; Polish American Newspapers.
Document Types:
Manuscripts.; Pamphlets.; Correspondence.; Photographs.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- General
  - Jedrzej Giertych-"Dzialalnosc narodowa Romana Galinskiego" from: Opoka, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dzialanosc narodowa Romana Galinskiego: moje spotkania z R.G. - Wstep do zyciorysu (manuscript), Feb 12, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - "Testament Romana Dmowskiego dla Polaka Amerykanina", 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re: Roman Dmowski's Message, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Corresp. re: distribution of "Testament", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Tytan zapoznany" editorial by M. Kosinski, (R.Galinski), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tytan zapoznany-manuscripts, corresp., 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roman Dmowski, biographical information, clippings, essays, 1939-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Rachunek sumienia" corresp., distr., 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Wspomnienia z Polski" R. Galinski, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - R.G. articles on Pilsudski's role in 1920 victory, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pilsudski - clippings, notes, essays, 1929-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Moszalki-Dyrdalki (Polemical pieces on J.Pilsudski), 1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gen. Haller's autograph, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Polemical press clippings, 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Historja odrodzonej Polski w swietle prawdy" Miroslaw Kosinski (Roman Galinski); "Rachunek sumienia" B. Niemczyk, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Ofensywa narodowa: o 'Zlotym Rogu' sanacji" J. Wiewiora, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kolo Stronnictwa Narodowego w Nowym Yorku - notes, announcements, correspondence, 1952-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: various photos of Roman Dmowski, Father Alexander Syski, Hanka Swiezewska and Antoni Drygas, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photograph of Msgr. L. Bojnowski among other unidentified persons, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Poprawki historyczne" by Jozef Pilsudski, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Przewodnik Katolicki"-correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Polemicals articles and letters, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Orchard Lake correspondence, review of "Poland", 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - R. Galinski-Tadeusz Bielecki correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - R.Galinski-Jedrzej Giertych 1963 ,J.Giertych-N. Siemaszko correspondence (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - J.Giertych (con't), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - R. Galinski-Edward Henzel correspondences, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence R. Galinski Karol Jaskolski (Gazeta Polonii), 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - R. Galinski-Szczepan Kotowicz-corresondence, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - R. Galinski-Stanislaw Kozanecki correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - R. Galinski-Michal Kwapiszewski correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - R. Galinski-Witold Olszewski correspondences, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - R. Galinski-Stanislaw Pyka correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - R. Galinski-Napoleon Siemaszko correspondence, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Walery Starczewski-correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Alexander Syski to R.G. correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - R. Galinski-Jan K. Tarnowski correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - F.J. Walus to R.G. correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jozef (Wiewiora?) to R.G. correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marian Wiszniewski to R.G. correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - R. Galinski-Romuald Wolikowski correspondence, 1961-1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Immigrants in New Britain - photocopies of articles from newspapers, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lafayette Newbrite Corp.: Jak mozemy wam pomoc? - pamphlet for immigrants, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Annual report of the City Mission, New Britain (photocopy), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Polish quislings in U.S.A.", 1939-1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Niech zyje Polska"-oswiadczenie Biura Polskiego New Yorskiego Komitetu Stanowego Partii Komunistycznej Stanow Zjednoczonych, Sep 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "O t.zw. przesileniu lipcowym", 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Armia polska" 9/5/40, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Paderewski prophecy by M. Bliss, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Copy of I. Paderewski's letter (statement?), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - List otwarty do pana Yollesa D. Woynicz, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dlaczego Harvard nie chcial przyjac Gen. Hallera?, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Napoleon Siemaszko - correspondence, biographical information, articles and clippings, 1938-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Opoka-subscriptions, distribution, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Father Syski: a tribute to his memory" by Bronislas A. Jezierski, [1945?] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - J. Giertych-letters to editors. Biographical information on J. Giertych, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Wilfred E. Mis Personal newsletter "Porozmawiajmy" NY, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Kolegium Zwiazku Narodowego Polskiego, katalog, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Przewrot majowy poczatkiem walki przeciw demokracji w Polsce" L.T. Walkowicz, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Wrazenia naocznego swiadka zpod drugiego zaboru", undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Prawda o zajsciach lwowskich", 1939 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Polish-American organization: invitations, found raising, etc, 1954-1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Anti-semitic pamphlets
  - Zydzi Panami swiata, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - My a Zydzi, J. Krzep, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Badacze i rozbijacze, K. Gajewski, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sprawa Najwazniejsza, K. Wierczak, [1934?] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Czarna siec, W. Zielinski, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Protokoly Medrcow Syjonu, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Zydzi w czasie walk o niepodleglosc Polski, Kazimierz Dolega, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Antysemici i nekrofile, A. Penzik, [1944] (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Rzad zydowski, T. Jeske-Choinski, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - O Zydach, T. Jeske-Choinski, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Dokad Zydzi daza?, T.Jeske-Choinski, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Co Zydzi robili w Polsce, T. Jeske-Choinski, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Nasz Program: konferencja krajowa Zwiazku Ludowo-Narodowego, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Narod rzadzacy, Wojciech Wasiutynski, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mocarstwa anonimowe, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 15)